<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>No Promises</title><link>http://www.johnxia.me/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.johnxia.me/feeds/john-xia.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2014 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Animusic</title><link>http://www.johnxia.me/animusic.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This year for the
&lt;a href="http://scavhunt.uchicago.edu/list2014_2final.pdf"&gt;Scavenger Hunt&lt;/a&gt; I
mostly worked on this item:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;49. Bring us an Animusic-style instrument that plays itself. Once
activated, it should perform, unaided, a composition of no less than
90 seconds. While your device may have electronic components, it must
not produce electronic
music. [175 points. 50 bonus points if the music is played by multiple distinct mechanisms that join in gradually as it proceeds]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw this item at around 3 in the morning on Thursday, a few hours
after the craziness of list release. It grabbed my attention, both
because I knew I was expected to do it and because instruments have
fascinated me for some time, though I'd never gathered the gumption to
make anything more than a simple didgeridoo. So I cast around in my
mind for ideas on how to make something like this in the next few
days. First I had to know what the judges wanted, so I looked up the
source material on YouTube:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/hyCIpKAIFyo" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, I needed some sort of mechanical actuator. Luckily, I had
kept some solenoids from my failed attempt at a water curtain
in 2013. Another quick YouTube search confirmed that it was possible
for solenoids to hit things hard enough to make sounds. Unfortunately
the solenoids I had were pulling solenoids, which are not optimal for
striking things. So I modeled a simple lever that the solenoid could
pull on, and a mount to keep everything in line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cut them out the next morning on the lasercutter at the
&lt;a href="http://arts.uchicago.edu/hack-arts-lab-hal"&gt;Hack Arts Lab&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately,
I had forgotten to get materials, so I had to use the scrap in the
shop. I ended up cutting the main levers out of 3/4" thick plywood,
which required 3 passes at high power and low speed to get
through. Even then I had to use a Dremel to fully separate the pieces
from the stock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some judicious application of superglue to skateboard bearings
ensued. I like using skateboard bearings for moving parts because
they're easy to get and relatively cheap. They also fit great on
things that are 5/16" in diameter, such as Bic pens. I like superglue
because I like taking risks and do not know fear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the superglue dried, I hooked up the whole apparatus to an
Arduino. The solenoids ran on 12V and 1.2A, which is far more than the
Arduino can output, so I needed to use some power transistors and an
external power source. Fortunately, I had planned ahead and converted
an old computer power supply into a serviceable benchtop power supply,
with binding posts for +12V, +5V, +3.3V, -5V, -12V, and GND. It even
had fancy things like short protection and everything! I got the power
transistors from RadioShack. Fat little suckers the size of your
fingernail, rated for 90W.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all the wiring was sorted it was relatively simple to get the
lever to move. All I had to do was send a 5V, 20ms pulse to the base
voltage on the transistor. Even with my limited knowledge of C I was
able to manage that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/animusic/animusic_arm.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It remained to wire up several more solenoid-lever modules so we could
play multiple instruments, and have some sort of method for writing
music. I ran into some issues which were solved by adding a '\0' to
the end of a string and felt like a greenhorn, but it all came
together pretty quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friend Zach, an incredibly talented drummer (and the captain of our
team), brought over his drumset on Saturday night. We spied some large
pieces of MDF that nobody was using, and made a nice big base for
everything. By 6:30 in the morning we had everything wired up and
ready. Zach took a quick nap and about half an hour later we had this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/w9Puv_iJRiE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We sat there watching it loop over and over, sleep-deprived,
triumphant, shocked and awed by our own magnificence. A teammate
snored loudly on the couch, somehow sleeping through everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then Zach scrapped all the music and re-wrote
it. &lt;a href="http://scavjudges.tumblr.com/post/85751911609/another-fabulous-completion-of-item-49-by-max"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt;
is the final result.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">John Xia</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.johnxia.me,2014-06-29:animusic.html</guid><category>Scav</category></item><item><title>Ordered and Indetermined</title><link>http://www.johnxia.me/ordered-indetermined.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Another project for my Data and Algorithms in Art class was to make
something "Ordered and Indetermined." This phrase was pretty much left
up to interpretation. I made some animations in JavaScript - this was
pretty much my introduction to the language. Screenshots follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first idea was to make a juggling siteswap visualizer, which the
professor thought was uninteresting. So I stopped at making bouncing
blocks. I wondered what it would look like if I just made a ton of
bouncing rectangles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.johnxia.me/ordered_indetermined/juggle.html"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://www.johnxia.me/blog/images/ordered-indetermined/juggle-view.jpg" style="width:400px;"&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Click for animation...&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next idea, which I eventually presented in class, was
"ElevatorCorp", an idealized simulation of an office building where
all the workers do is ride elevators all day. I used
&lt;a href="http://threejs.org/"&gt;three.js&lt;/a&gt; to talk to WebGL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.johnxia.me/ordered_indetermined/elevators.html"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://www.johnxia.me/blog/images/ordered-indetermined/elevatorcorp.jpg"&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Click for animation...&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">John Xia</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2014 11:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.johnxia.me,2014-05-20:ordered-indetermined.html</guid></item><item><title>HvZ Catapult</title><link>http://www.johnxia.me/hvz-catapult.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;For my last game of &lt;a href="http://www.uchicagohvz.org"&gt;Humans vs. Zombies&lt;/a&gt; I
decided that I would utilize the least effective strategy possible. I
optimized my weaponry for highest visibility, lowest mobility, and
lowest zombie-killing ability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, naturally, I went to the shop, found some scrap wood, and threw
together a back-mounted catapult, powered by twisted up bandanas of
HvZ's past. When that proved to be a little bit too pathetic I added
some rubber bands, increasing the range to about 30 feet. To defend
myself from zombies I needed to either set the catapult on the ground,
or get a nearby friend to be my gunner as I crouched down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not kill any zombies with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.johnxia.me/blog/images/hvz-catapult/catapult-1.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.johnxia.me/blog/images/hvz-catapult/catapult-2.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.johnxia.me/blog/images/hvz-catapult/catapult-3.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">John Xia</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.johnxia.me,2014-05-20:hvz-catapult.html</guid></item><item><title>Water Blob</title><link>http://www.johnxia.me/water-blob.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/water-blob/projection-far.JPG"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quarter I am in &lt;a href="http://www.salavon.com"&gt;Jason Salavon&lt;/a&gt;'s Data
and Algorithm in Art class. This is a group project I did with
&lt;a href="http://clarekoury.tumblr.com"&gt;Clare Koury&lt;/a&gt; and Rebeca Carillo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hooked up a PC fan to an Arduino and had it pulse briefly every
couple seconds. The fan had a magnet attached to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/water-blob/pool-side.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of the fan we put a CD spindle with some
&lt;a href="http://www.instructables.com/id/Making-Rheoscopic-Fluid/?ALLSTEPS"&gt;rheoscopic fluid&lt;/a&gt;
in it. To agitate the liquid we used
&lt;a href="http://shapelock.com/"&gt;Shapelock&lt;/a&gt; to encase another magnet. Basically
we made a magnetic stirrer that only worked part of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/water-blob/pool-top.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a video of me discovering that the fan goes too fast for the
magnetic coupling. We solved this by pulsing the fan for about 40ms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="420" height="315"
src="//www.youtube.com/embed/a6MGmMGI2XQ" frameborder="0"
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we made a pedestal for it, added a camera that provided a live
feed to a projector, and shined a bright light on it. All the pieces
came together in about half an hour. It working at all was pretty
surprising, I thought, so when people thought it had artistic merit as
well I was doubly suprised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/yCI13KS8Hrw" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional images:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/water-blob/long-view.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/water-blob/apparatus.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pictures courtesy of Clare Koury.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">John Xia</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.johnxia.me,2014-05-20:water-blob.html</guid></item><item><title>Swingy Arm Thing</title><link>http://www.johnxia.me/swingy-arm-thing.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I was in an art class last quarter, taught by &lt;a href="http://www.hannahgivler.com"&gt;Hannah Givler&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is called "Module Matters". The prompt is to make a
reproducible module that can be used as a building block or an
integral part of a sculpture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially I was doing a bunch of research on 3-D tiling, but I got distracted by
magnets and started thinking about cool magnetic things instead. After some
excited discussion with my friend Rachel I decided to CAD up a swingy arm thing
with magnets. The basic idea is that I have a stack of rotating arms
with magnets in their ends - this causes them to be loosely coupled in that
strange magnetic way. Then when you move any of the arms, the others move with
it. It's reminiscent of the
&lt;a href="http://exs.exploratorium.edu/exhibits/magnetic-wave-machine/"&gt;Magnetic Wave Machine&lt;/a&gt;
at the Exploratorium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I printed out a template from SolidWorks and traced that onto a scrap piece of lauan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/swingy-arm-thing/paper-template.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cut it out with a bandsaw, then sanded it down.  Then I nailed a few
pieces of scrap together, using the template as a template, to make a
quick jig so I can drill holes precisely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/swingy-arm-thing/lauan-in-jig.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I traced the template 10 times onto a 2'x4' piece of 3/4" plywood, and cut
them all out with a bandsaw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/swingy-arm-thing/rough-cut.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I used the template to route out the pieces smoothly, before
putting them in the drilling jig to make the pockets for the magnets
and bearings.  I used skateboard bearings, because they're cheap and
easy to find. They take 8mm axles, which is just a smidge bigger than
the 5/16" threaded rod I used for the axle. The arms were spaced out
with washers between the bearings and secured with a nut on each end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is some video of the first few arms, hanging out in the joining
table:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315"
src="//www.youtube.com/embed/RuilwwdHYTs?rel=0" frameborder="0"
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn't really thought about how I would mount the piece. After a
discussion with my professor I decided to cobble together some 2x4's
and call it a day. I'm not proud of that, but the truth is the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/swingy-arm-thing/finished.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">John Xia</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>tag:www.johnxia.me,2014-02-07:swingy-arm-thing.html</guid><category>magnets</category><category>wood</category></item><item><title>Bamboo Bike</title><link>http://www.johnxia.me/bamboo-bike.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In high school I built some bamboo bikes. The second one broke and I rebuilt it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are their stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;v0.1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day I was biking with my friend Chris. I said to him that we should build a
bamboo bike in the summer. He said that that was a great idea and that we should
do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When summer started we bummed for bike parts around Palo Alto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somebody gave us an old frame that had been in a crash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/bamboo-bike/broken-frame.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We sawed the joints off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/bamboo-bike/joints.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we went to a bamboo garden in the hills and got some bamboo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We heat-treated the bamboo, which both dries the bamboo and strengthens it. Then
we cut it into appropriate lengths and fit them onto the steel joints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/bamboo-bike/v01-layout.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bamboo was loose on the steel tubes, so we filled the space with expanding
foam. Then we mixed up some epoxy resin, soaked twine in it, and wrapped
that around the joints to strengthen them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final product had some pretty wonky geometry, which was totally
different from what we had laid out earlier:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/bamboo-bike/finished-v01.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bottom bracket holder was very low to the ground, resulting in low ground
clearance. I had to be very careful to avoid pedal strike. I resolved to use a
jig the next time around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;v0.2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next summer, having learned many lessons, I built another bike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/bamboo-bike/finished-v02.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was happy enough to make an
&lt;a href="http://www.instructables.com/id/Bamboo-Bike-Frame/"&gt;Instructable&lt;/a&gt; about the
build process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I rode this daily for several months, then one day the bottom bracket joint
snapped as I was crossing a street. So I started thinking about the next one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/bamboo-bike/riding-v02.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;v0.3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this one I redid the joints that broke with carbon fiber:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/bamboo-bike/finished-v03.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First I tacked the joints back together. Then I built up the joints with
long-fiber Bondo, a two-part putty reinforced with fiberglass. I smoothed the
Bondo out with a Dremel, and started laminating the joint with carbon fiber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found a vacuum pump, made an air filter with activated charcoal and a metal
can, and bought some trash-bags. Then I was able to do some
&lt;a href="http://ezinearticles.com/?Vacuum-Bagging-Carbon-Fiber-On-$50&amp;amp;id=674586"&gt;crude vacuum-bagging&lt;/a&gt;
of the joints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I waited for the epoxy to cure, I thought of a couple other ways I could have
joined the bamboo - forming the joints with smooth Bondo, using small bamboo
gussets, etc. The idea is to minimize the probability of kinks and air pockets
in the fiber by making the joint as smooth as possible. I'll have to test to see
which method works best.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">John Xia</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.johnxia.me,2013-09-05:bamboo-bike.html</guid><category>bicycles</category></item><item><title>Tensegrity</title><link>http://www.johnxia.me/tensegrity.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One day I was reminiscing about my childhood and remembered seeing a cool
sculpture made only with steel tubes and cable. A bit of Googling revealed that
this was a
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tensegrity"&gt;tensegrity structure&lt;/a&gt;. Tensegrity is
cool because it uses cables and rods to make a stiff structure without having
the rods touch each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided that I would make one myself. So for the next week or so, I got a few
forks every time I went to the dining hall. Some fishing-line and some dremeling ensued, and here is the result!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/tensegrity/tensegrity.jpg" style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">John Xia</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.johnxia.me,2013-08-31:tensegrity.html</guid><category>"art"</category></item><item><title>Scav 2011-2013</title><link>http://www.johnxia.me/scav.html</link><description>&lt;h3&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every year, I partake in a four-day journey into madness called Scav (short for
the University of Chicago Scavenger Hunt). There are several teams of a few
dozen each; on the Wednesday night before Mother's Day we gather to receive the
&lt;a href="http://scavhunt.uchicago.edu/list2014final.pdf"&gt;List&lt;/a&gt;, which contains around
300 eccentric items. Then we madly sprint to complete as many items as
possible. On Mother's Day itself we gather to show off what we have scraped
together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few of the items I've worked on through the years. They're
not... pretty. Think of them as early-stage prototypes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2011&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first year. I didn't know that there was a "Big Projects" group specializing
in construction, so I signed up to take care of a page of the List. Here are
some of the items from my page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Lamp&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;37. One of those cheap, many-headed colorful dorm floor lamps. [1 point
per head, 30 bonus points if they can move unaided, 10 bonus bonus
points if it is tearing apart a small ship]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/scav/lamp.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mechanism was inspired by toys that look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/scav/chicken-toy.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You swing the ball around, pulling on the string going to each chicken's
head. This moves them up and down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We didn't have motors, so to "move the heads unaided" I used a pulley and a
weight. We didn't have those either. I rigged up a pulley with cardboard taped
to a pipe. This rested inside a larger section of pipe so it could spin
freely. The weight was three water bottles in a plastic bag. I added rubber
bands to add tension to the string and move the heads back to their initial
positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Eyes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;40. Affix a pair of appropriately enormous googly eyes to the campus
building of your choice. [8 points]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/scav/eyes.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had planned on dangling them off the edge of the tower with wires. I
envisioned them swaying gently in the wind, pupils googling like mad for the
world to see. Getting these up wasn't hard - we just went up the stairs. Once we
got to the top, we found that the wind was too strong and the eyes flapped
wildly. Fortunately, we had duct tape and just leaned over the edge to secure
the eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2012&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, all the previous Big Projects folks had split, so I was heading up a
Big Projects team of one person (me). I holed up and worked on these items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Piano&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;146. Play me a drink, Sam, for old times’ sake...on your piano that
dispenses a beverage component with every keystroke. Changing the
melody should change the mixology. Instruments and their compositions
will be judged both on the quality of the cocktails and the musicality
of their recipes. [250 points, 25 extra points if your keyboard can
play a different melody to create a different drink]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/scav/pianoclose.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a little bit hacked together.
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mounted bottles filled with liquor (or mixer) on axles so their neutral
position would be right-side-up. I found these
&lt;a href="http://www.sciplus.com/p/POWER-DOOR-LOCK_47851"&gt;automotive door lock actuators&lt;/a&gt;
at ASS that would push upwards a few inches when I applied a voltage across
them. I attached the bottles so they would tip when the actuators fired. I
hooked up wires to a mini keyboard, turning each key into a switch that
activated one of the bottles. Now each note played corresponded to some alcohol
poured! The alcohol went through a 10-inch funnel into a glass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Map&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;264. King’s Landing and The Twins are all right, I guess, but we’d
rather see something a little more neo-Gothic. Produce a map of the U
of C campus that when triggered erects a clockwork version of a campus
building of your choice. [175 points]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had to present this at 9:00 AM on Sunday. So we started at 6:00 that
morning. We had gears lying around, but no shafts. Luckily, the box of pens we
had bought were a great fit! So I got busy making a replica of the chapel I had
hung eyes from the year before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/scav/map.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of many things we did not have time to make was a stand to hold it up.
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, ours was the only one with a building that had moving gears on
it. However, the motor that was supposed to lift the building up from under the
map burned out when we were presenting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During these three hours I learned how hard it was to work with foamcore
poster-board. But I forgot all about that when I started on Aquagraphics in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2013&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I assembled a Big Projects team! We could plan items together, build
them together, all that jazz. I spent a lot more time with the rest of the team,
helping people with their own technical items. This was much more fun than
working alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Liver&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;84. Take us on a Fantastic Voyage through your team’s larger-than-life
model of a human organ. Your structure must be able to comfortably
accommodate at least four tourists at a time and present an accurate
and informative account of the organ’s inner workings. We’ll happily
enter the body part of your choice, but remember that our heart belongs
to the Franklin Institute. [150 points]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/scav/liver-whole.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we are, shooing people into the liver.
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After much deliberation we settled on a liver. Because I like steel, we bought a
ton of electrical conduit and bent it into a frame. It was much lighter and
stiffer than a comparable wooden or PVC one. We covered it in about 80 feet of
chicken wire. When we started tarping the liver, we found that it was so light
that it blew away! So we got some rope and stakes to keep it on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/scav/liver-internal.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We filled the inside with clear plastic tubes to represent the tubes inside the
liver. We hooked up some "bodily fluids" to the tubes: a bottle of sweet tea
vodka for bile and red Gatorade for blood. We also had long twisty balloons so
visitors could "fold their own proteins."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/scav/liver-faces.jpg" 
style="width: 400px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the people who helped!
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Aquagraphics Curtain&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;208. An aquagraphic-style water curtain that displays your team name or
logo. [250 points]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://http://jdangerx.github.io/blog/208.html"&gt;See my other post.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">John Xia</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.johnxia.me,2013-08-30:scav.html</guid><category>scav</category></item><item><title>FourthApp</title><link>http://www.johnxia.me/fourth-app.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm currently an intern at
&lt;a href="http://www.missionst.com/"&gt;Mission St. Manufacturing&lt;/a&gt;. We're a 3D
printing company that's trying to streamline 3D printing. If you're
not familiar with 3D printers, imagine building up an object with a
hot glue gun, carefully squeezing out layer upon layer of
plastic. That is exactly what a 3D printer does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the problems we are fixing is that you have to jump through a
ton of hoops to print something. Making a 3D model is hard. Once you
have a model you have to turn that into instructions for your printer,
and once you have the instructions, you have to actually print
them. We hide most of this on our server so nobody has to deal
with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can't hide the actual modeling, so we're making tablet apps that
make simple 3D modeling &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; simple.  We've got a few in the
works. Let's take a look at one that turns your finger drawings into
real things that you can hold. Its code name is FourthApp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you draw something. It's kind of like Paint. No spray-can, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/fourth-app/drawView.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you hit print preview. We turn it into a 3D model and send it
back down for your perusal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/fourth-app/previewView.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it turns out satisfactorily you can choose to print your part:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/fourth-app/printing.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which ends up looking like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/fourth-app/part.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are, no doubt, curious as to how this all works. I'd love to tell
you, but first we need to understand the basics. Namely, what does
making a 3D model entail? Conceptually, it's pretty easy - you take a
picture, figure out what you want the model to look like, and draw
triangles on the model until it's all covered, like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/fourth-app/meshlab.jpg" alt="This is grabbed from an
open-source program called MeshLab." style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have that, you can cut it into thin horizontal slices; then
you can write instructions to tell the printer how to move on each
layer. This process is called &lt;em&gt;toolpath generation&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;slicing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the devil is in the details. We tried several different ways
of making models, which can be lumped into one of two categories:
path-based and image-based.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started with a path-based method, which works like this: we track
the path the finger traces across the screen. Then we draw two paths
on either side, marking the bottom edges of the model. Then we play
connect-the-dots and make the triangles for the bottom face. Next we
make a copy of the bottom and move it up to make the top
face. Finally, we connect the top and bottom faces to each other to
make the sides. Ta-da!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This runs into some problems, though, when the path crosses over
itself. We end up with some triangles inside the model! The internal
triangles make it hard to determine the border of each slice. This
really messes with your toolpaths. We decided to try to detect the
self-intersections. This worked by checking each edge against each
other edge to see if they crossed. This is slow - when you start
drawing complex pictures, the brush noticeably lags behind your finger
as we accumulate more edges to check.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While trying to fix the code we started thinking about other
approaches. What if we took a screenshot and turned that into a 3D
model? We'd avoid the self-intersecting paths altogether - once you
have painted an area black, it doesn't matter if you go over it
again. It will still be black. It will be black until the end-times,
no matter how many times you draw over it. This was really exciting!
So we started hacking on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon we had something that kind of worked. The idea is pretty simple:
you look at each pixel in the picture, keeping track of how dark each
pixel is. This will correspond to height later. Each pixel has a 2D
position already. You can put that together with the heights you just
found to get a bunch of 3D points. Then you draw a bunch of triangles
in a giant game of connect-the-three-dimensional-dots, and voila! You
have a 3D model!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This method makes a lot of triangles. In fact, it makes about 10 times
as many as the last one. This means it's 10 times bigger, 10 times
harder to send over the Internet, 10 times harder to slice. To
alleviate these problems, we shrunk down the resolution of the images,
but ran into another snag: at such low resolutions, the beautiful,
organic curves (sensuous, even) that people were drawing became jagged
pixelated blocks. That can be helpful if you are trying to print out
characters from Super Mario, but that's not exactly what we want.  We
tried to find a happy medium between slow and pretty, but it wasn't
there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we've hacked together another solution. The benefit of the
path-based approach is that the model itself is much smaller and
simpler; the benefit of the image-based approach is that we don't have
to deal with self-intersecting curves. A hybrid solution gets us both
of these. The app sends us a picture of what the user has drawn. Then
we use a nice program called
&lt;a href="http://potrace.sourceforge.net/"&gt;potrace&lt;/a&gt; to trace the edges of the
drawing. From there, we connect the dots and get a model which is as
simple and smooth as a path-based one without any of the
self-intersection issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there's still ways to improve. I'm working on an extension
to this hybrid method that will let you use different shades of grey
in your drawing to indicate different thicknesses. We can trace those
edges with potrace to get the profile of each slice. Then we can stack
them on top of each other to create the model. This lets you make
things that are bumpy on top. You'd &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; be getting somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astute readers may notice that we don't need to turn the picture into
triangles to make toolpaths. All the printer does is fill in one
horizontal slice of the object and move up, so if we know what each
slice looks like we can make toolpaths straight from that. Luckily,
the different levels of grey represent exactly that! Instead of
stacking the slices, turning that into triangles, then slicing up the
triangles again, we can skip that middle step. This business of
translating between slices and triangles gets into deep waters very
quickly, though, and deserves its own post.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">John Xia</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.johnxia.me,2013-08-13:fourth-app.html</guid><category>3D printing</category><category>code</category></item></channel></rss>