<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>No Promises</title><link href="http://www.johnxia.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.johnxia.me/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.johnxia.me/</id><updated>2014-11-23T00:00:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>The Speed of News</title><link href="http://www.johnxia.me/speed-of-news.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-11-23T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>John Xia</name></author><id>tag:www.johnxia.me,2014-11-23:speed-of-news.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In college, I was fortunate enough to take a course on Sumerian
literature from &lt;a href="http://nelc.uchicago.edu/faculty/woods"&gt;Christopher Woods&lt;/a&gt;. We learned, among other
things, that in ancient Sumeria places that were far away were also
somehow farther in the past. This is roughly similar to the
correspondence between space and time which we study in
relativity. Why did the Sumerians find space-time unification so
natural? In my &lt;a href="/misc/NEHC_final.pdf"&gt;final paper&lt;/a&gt;, I argued that at the core of both
conceptions of space-time was the limited speed of information. In
ancient Sumeria, the speed of information was much slower than the
speed of light, and thus the time-bending effects of space were more
evident. Fortunately, Dr. Woods was a physics student in his youth and
let me get away with writing 10 pages about physics for my
Civilization Studies course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several years later and a couple weeks ago, I participated in the
&lt;a href="https://hack.uchicago.edu"&gt;hack@UChicago&lt;/a&gt; Fall Hackathon on a whim. I was tooting around
after the workshops, trying to figure out what to make, when I
remembered that paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to make a &lt;a href="/relativity"&gt;map&lt;/a&gt; that would let you see what
sort of news you would be hearing from around the world if news
traveled at human speeds. The blue (draggable) marker is your current
location. You can click the map to find the news that you would be
hearing from there. There's a dropdown menu with different news
speeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make the map, I used a simple &lt;a href="http://leafletjs.com/"&gt;Leaflet&lt;/a&gt; map with a &lt;a href="http://mapbox.com/"&gt;Mapbox&lt;/a&gt;
tile layer.  I use the Mapbox geocoder to find the location of your
click; it is, regrettably, of little use outside of the United States
and southern Canada. I use the &lt;a href="http://developer.nytimes.com/docs/read/article_search_api_v2"&gt;New York Times Article Search API&lt;/a&gt; to
find news from that location; it has similar regional
problems. Unfortunately the Google News API was deprecated long ago.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Animusic</title><link href="http://www.johnxia.me/animusic.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>John Xia</name></author><id>tag:www.johnxia.me,2014-06-29:animusic.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This year for the
&lt;a href="http://scavhunt.uchicago.edu/list2014_2final.pdf"&gt;Scavenger Hunt&lt;/a&gt; I
mostly worked on this item:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;49. Bring us an Animusic-style instrument that plays itself. Once
activated, it should perform, unaided, a composition of no less than
90 seconds. While your device may have electronic components, it must
not produce electronic
music. [175 points. 50 bonus points if the music is played by multiple distinct mechanisms that join in gradually as it proceeds]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw this item at around 3 in the morning on Thursday, a few hours
after the craziness of list release. It grabbed my attention, both
because I knew I was expected to do it and because instruments have
fascinated me for some time, though I'd never gathered the gumption to
make anything more than a simple didgeridoo. So I cast around in my
mind for ideas on how to make something like this in the next few
days. First I had to know what the judges wanted, so I looked up the
source material on YouTube:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/hyCIpKAIFyo" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, I needed some sort of mechanical actuator. Luckily, I had
kept some solenoids from my failed attempt at a water curtain
in 2013. Another quick YouTube search confirmed that it was possible
for solenoids to hit things hard enough to make sounds. Unfortunately
the solenoids I had were pulling solenoids, which are not optimal for
striking things. So I modeled a simple lever that the solenoid could
pull on, and a mount to keep everything in line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cut them out the next morning on the lasercutter at the
&lt;a href="http://arts.uchicago.edu/hack-arts-lab-hal"&gt;Hack Arts Lab&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately,
I had forgotten to get materials, so I had to use the scrap in the
shop. I ended up cutting the main levers out of 3/4" thick plywood,
which required 3 passes at high power and low speed to get
through. Even then I had to use a Dremel to fully separate the pieces
from the stock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some judicious application of superglue to skateboard bearings
ensued. I like using skateboard bearings for moving parts because
they're easy to get and relatively cheap. They also fit great on
things that are 5/16" in diameter, such as Bic pens. I like superglue
because I like taking risks and do not know fear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the superglue dried, I hooked up the whole apparatus to an
Arduino. The solenoids ran on 12V and 1.2A, which is far more than the
Arduino can output, so I needed to use some power transistors and an
external power source. Fortunately, I had planned ahead and converted
an old computer power supply into a serviceable benchtop power supply,
with binding posts for +12V, +5V, +3.3V, -5V, -12V, and GND. It even
had fancy things like short protection and everything! I got the power
transistors from RadioShack. Fat little suckers the size of your
fingernail, rated for 90W.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all the wiring was sorted it was relatively simple to get the
lever to move. All I had to do was send a 5V, 20ms pulse to the base
voltage on the transistor. Even with my limited knowledge of C I was
able to manage that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/animusic/animusic_arm.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It remained to wire up several more solenoid-lever modules so we could
play multiple instruments, and have some sort of method for writing
music. I ran into some issues which were solved by adding a '\0' to
the end of a string and felt like a greenhorn, but it all came
together pretty quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friend Zach, an incredibly talented drummer (and the captain of our
team), brought over his drumset on Saturday night. We spied some large
pieces of MDF that nobody was using, and made a nice big base for
everything. By 6:30 in the morning we had everything wired up and
ready. Zach took a quick nap and about half an hour later we had this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/w9Puv_iJRiE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We sat there watching it loop over and over, sleep-deprived,
triumphant, shocked and awed by our own magnificence. A teammate
snored loudly on the couch, somehow sleeping through everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then Zach scrapped all the music and re-wrote
it. &lt;a href="http://scavjudges.tumblr.com/post/85751911609/another-fabulous-completion-of-item-49-by-max"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt;
is the final result.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Scav"></category></entry><entry><title>Ordered and Indetermined</title><link href="http://www.johnxia.me/ordered-indetermined.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-05-20T11:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>John Xia</name></author><id>tag:www.johnxia.me,2014-05-20:ordered-indetermined.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another project for my Data and Algorithms in Art class was to make
something "Ordered and Indetermined." This phrase was pretty much left
up to interpretation. I made some animations in JavaScript - this was
pretty much my introduction to the language. Screenshots follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first idea was to make a juggling siteswap visualizer, which the
professor thought was uninteresting. So I stopped at making bouncing
blocks. I wondered what it would look like if I just made a ton of
bouncing rectangles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/ordered_indetermined/juggle.html"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/ordered-indetermined/juggle-view.jpg" style="width:400px;"&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Click for animation...&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next idea, which I eventually presented in class, was
"ElevatorCorp", an idealized simulation of an office building where
all the workers do is ride elevators all day. I used
&lt;a href="http://threejs.org/"&gt;three.js&lt;/a&gt; to talk to WebGL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/ordered_indetermined/elevators.html"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/ordered-indetermined/elevatorcorp.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>HvZ Catapult</title><link href="http://www.johnxia.me/hvz-catapult.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-05-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>John Xia</name></author><id>tag:www.johnxia.me,2014-05-20:hvz-catapult.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For my last game of &lt;a href="http://www.uchicagohvz.org"&gt;Humans vs. Zombies&lt;/a&gt; I
decided that I would utilize the least effective strategy possible. I
optimized my weaponry for highest visibility, lowest mobility, and
lowest zombie-killing ability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, naturally, I went to the shop, found some scrap wood, and threw
together a back-mounted catapult, powered by twisted up bandanas of
HvZ's past. When that proved to be a little bit too pathetic I added
some rubber bands, increasing the range to about 30 feet. To defend
myself from zombies I needed to either set the catapult on the ground,
or get a nearby friend to be my gunner as I crouched down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not tag any zombies with this, though not for lack of trying. My
friend and I went hunting for them on my way to class - the zombie who
tagged me didn't even realize I was playing until we started hooting
and hollering and gently lobbing socks at him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/hvz-catapult/catapult-1.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/hvz-catapult/catapult-2.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/hvz-catapult/catapult-3.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Water Blob</title><link href="http://www.johnxia.me/water-blob.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-05-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>John Xia</name></author><id>tag:www.johnxia.me,2014-05-20:water-blob.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/water-blob/projection-far.JPG"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quarter I am in &lt;a href="http://www.salavon.com"&gt;Jason Salavon&lt;/a&gt;'s Data
and Algorithm in Art class. This is a group project I did with
&lt;a href="http://clarekoury.tumblr.com"&gt;Clare Koury&lt;/a&gt; and Rebeca Carillo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hooked up a PC fan to an Arduino and had it pulse briefly every
couple seconds. The fan had a magnet attached to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/water-blob/pool-side.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of the fan we put a CD spindle with some
&lt;a href="http://www.instructables.com/id/Making-Rheoscopic-Fluid/?ALLSTEPS"&gt;rheoscopic fluid&lt;/a&gt;
in it. To agitate the liquid we used
&lt;a href="http://shapelock.com/"&gt;Shapelock&lt;/a&gt; to encase another magnet. Basically
we made a magnetic stirrer that only worked part of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/water-blob/pool-top.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a video of me discovering that the fan goes too fast for the
magnetic coupling. We solved this by pulsing the fan for about 40ms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="420" height="315"
src="//www.youtube.com/embed/a6MGmMGI2XQ" frameborder="0"
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we made a pedestal for it, added a camera that provided a live
feed to a projector, and shined a bright light on it. All the pieces
came together in about half an hour. It working at all was pretty
surprising, I thought, so when people thought it had artistic merit as
well I was doubly suprised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/yCI13KS8Hrw" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional images:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/water-blob/long-view.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/water-blob/apparatus.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pictures courtesy of Clare Koury.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>