<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>No Promises</title><link href="http://www.johnxia.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.johnxia.me/feeds/not-software.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.johnxia.me/</id><updated>2014-02-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>Swingy Arm Thing</title><link href="http://www.johnxia.me/swingy-arm-thing.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>John Xia</name></author><id>tag:www.johnxia.me,2014-02-07:swingy-arm-thing.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was in an art class last quarter, taught by &lt;a href="http://www.hannahgivler.com"&gt;Hannah Givler&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is called "Module Matters". The prompt is to make a
reproducible module that can be used as a building block or an
integral part of a sculpture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially I was doing a bunch of research on 3-D tiling, but I got distracted by
magnets and started thinking about cool magnetic things instead. After some
excited discussion with my friend Rachel I decided to CAD up a swingy arm thing
with magnets. The basic idea is that I have a stack of rotating arms
with magnets in their ends - this causes them to be loosely coupled in that
strange magnetic way. Then when you move any of the arms, the others move with
it. It's reminiscent of the
&lt;a href="http://exs.exploratorium.edu/exhibits/magnetic-wave-machine/"&gt;Magnetic Wave Machine&lt;/a&gt;
at the Exploratorium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I printed out a template from SolidWorks and traced that onto a scrap piece of lauan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/swingy-arm-thing/paper-template.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cut it out with a bandsaw, then sanded it down.  Then I nailed a few
pieces of scrap together, using the template as a template, to make a
quick jig so I can drill holes precisely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/swingy-arm-thing/lauan-in-jig.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I traced the template 10 times onto a 2'x4' piece of 3/4" plywood, and cut
them all out with a bandsaw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/swingy-arm-thing/rough-cut.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I used the template to route out the pieces smoothly, before
putting them in the drilling jig to make the pockets for the magnets
and bearings.  I used skateboard bearings, because they're cheap and
easy to find. They take 8mm axles, which is just a smidge bigger than
the 5/16" threaded rod I used for the axle. The arms were spaced out
with washers between the bearings and secured with a nut on each end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is some video of the first few arms, hanging out in the joining
table:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315"
src="//www.youtube.com/embed/RuilwwdHYTs?rel=0" frameborder="0"
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn't really thought about how I would mount the piece. After a
discussion with my professor I decided to cobble together some 2x4's
and call it a day. I'm not proud of that, but the truth is the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/swingy-arm-thing/finished.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="magnets"></category><category term="wood"></category></entry><entry><title>Bamboo Bike</title><link href="http://www.johnxia.me/bamboo-bike.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-09-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>John Xia</name></author><id>tag:www.johnxia.me,2013-09-05:bamboo-bike.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In high school I built some bamboo bikes. The second one broke and I rebuilt it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are their stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;v0.1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day I was biking with my friend Chris. I said to him that we should build a
bamboo bike in the summer. He said that that was a great idea and that we should
do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When summer started we bummed for bike parts around Palo Alto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somebody gave us an old frame that had been in a crash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/bamboo-bike/broken-frame.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We sawed the joints off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/bamboo-bike/joints.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we went to a bamboo garden in the hills and got some bamboo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We heat-treated the bamboo, which both dries the bamboo and strengthens it. Then
we cut it into appropriate lengths and fit them onto the steel joints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/bamboo-bike/v01-layout.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bamboo was loose on the steel tubes, so we filled the space with expanding
foam. Then we mixed up some epoxy resin, soaked twine in it, and wrapped
that around the joints to strengthen them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final product had some pretty wonky geometry, which was totally
different from what we had laid out earlier:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/bamboo-bike/finished-v01.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bottom bracket holder was very low to the ground, resulting in low ground
clearance. I had to be very careful to avoid pedal strike. I resolved to use a
jig the next time around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;v0.2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next summer, having learned many lessons, I built another bike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/bamboo-bike/finished-v02.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was happy enough to make an
&lt;a href="http://www.instructables.com/id/Bamboo-Bike-Frame/"&gt;Instructable&lt;/a&gt; about the
build process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I rode this daily for several months, then one day the bottom bracket joint
snapped as I was crossing a street. So I started thinking about the next one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/bamboo-bike/riding-v02.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;v0.3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this one I redid the joints that broke with carbon fiber:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/bamboo-bike/finished-v03.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First I tacked the joints back together. Then I built up the joints with
long-fiber Bondo, a two-part putty reinforced with fiberglass. I smoothed the
Bondo out with a Dremel, and started laminating the joint with carbon fiber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found a vacuum pump, made an air filter with activated charcoal and a metal
can, and bought some trash-bags. Then I was able to do some
&lt;a href="http://ezinearticles.com/?Vacuum-Bagging-Carbon-Fiber-On-$50&amp;amp;id=674586"&gt;crude vacuum-bagging&lt;/a&gt;
of the joints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I waited for the epoxy to cure, I thought of a couple other ways I could have
joined the bamboo - forming the joints with smooth Bondo, using small bamboo
gussets, etc. The idea is to minimize the probability of kinks and air pockets
in the fiber by making the joint as smooth as possible. I'll have to test to see
which method works best.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="bicycles"></category></entry><entry><title>Tensegrity</title><link href="http://www.johnxia.me/tensegrity.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-08-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>John Xia</name></author><id>tag:www.johnxia.me,2013-08-31:tensegrity.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One day I was reminiscing about my childhood and remembered seeing a cool
sculpture made only with steel tubes and cable. A bit of Googling revealed that
this was a
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tensegrity"&gt;tensegrity structure&lt;/a&gt;. Tensegrity is
cool because it uses cables and rods to make a stiff structure without having
the rods touch each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided that I would make one myself. So for the next week or so, I got a few
forks every time I went to the dining hall. Some fishing-line and some dremeling ensued, and here is the result!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/tensegrity/tensegrity.jpg" style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term='"art"'></category></entry><entry><title>Scav 2011-2013</title><link href="http://www.johnxia.me/scav.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-08-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>John Xia</name></author><id>tag:www.johnxia.me,2013-08-30:scav.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every year, I partake in a four-day journey into madness called Scav (short for
the University of Chicago Scavenger Hunt). There are several teams of a few
dozen each; on the Wednesday night before Mother's Day we gather to receive the
&lt;a href="http://scavhunt.uchicago.edu/list2014final.pdf"&gt;List&lt;/a&gt;, which contains around
300 eccentric items. Then we madly sprint to complete as many items as
possible. On Mother's Day itself we gather to show off what we have scraped
together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few of the items I've worked on through the years. They're
not... pretty. Think of them as early-stage prototypes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2011&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first year. I didn't know that there was a "Big Projects" group specializing
in construction, so I signed up to take care of a page of the List. Here are
some of the items from my page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Lamp&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;37. One of those cheap, many-headed colorful dorm floor lamps. [1 point
per head, 30 bonus points if they can move unaided, 10 bonus bonus
points if it is tearing apart a small ship]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/scav/lamp.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mechanism was inspired by toys that look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/scav/chicken-toy.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You swing the ball around, pulling on the string going to each chicken's
head. This moves them up and down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We didn't have motors, so to "move the heads unaided" I used a pulley and a
weight. We didn't have those either. I rigged up a pulley with cardboard taped
to a pipe. This rested inside a larger section of pipe so it could spin
freely. The weight was three water bottles in a plastic bag. I added rubber
bands to add tension to the string and move the heads back to their initial
positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Eyes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;40. Affix a pair of appropriately enormous googly eyes to the campus
building of your choice. [8 points]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/scav/eyes.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had planned on dangling them off the edge of the tower with wires. I
envisioned them swaying gently in the wind, pupils googling like mad for the
world to see. Getting these up wasn't hard - we just went up the stairs. Once we
got to the top, we found that the wind was too strong and the eyes flapped
wildly. Fortunately, we had duct tape and just leaned over the edge to secure
the eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2012&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, all the previous Big Projects folks had split, so I was heading up a
Big Projects team of one person (me). I holed up and worked on these items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Piano&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;146. Play me a drink, Sam, for old times’ sake...on your piano that
dispenses a beverage component with every keystroke. Changing the
melody should change the mixology. Instruments and their compositions
will be judged both on the quality of the cocktails and the musicality
of their recipes. [250 points, 25 extra points if your keyboard can
play a different melody to create a different drink]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/scav/pianoclose.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a little bit hacked together.
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mounted bottles filled with liquor (or mixer) on axles so their neutral
position would be right-side-up. I found these
&lt;a href="http://www.sciplus.com/p/POWER-DOOR-LOCK_47851"&gt;automotive door lock actuators&lt;/a&gt;
at ASS that would push upwards a few inches when I applied a voltage across
them. I attached the bottles so they would tip when the actuators fired. I
hooked up wires to a mini keyboard, turning each key into a switch that
activated one of the bottles. Now each note played corresponded to some alcohol
poured! The alcohol went through a 10-inch funnel into a glass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Map&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;264. King’s Landing and The Twins are all right, I guess, but we’d
rather see something a little more neo-Gothic. Produce a map of the U
of C campus that when triggered erects a clockwork version of a campus
building of your choice. [175 points]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had to present this at 9:00 AM on Sunday. So we started at 6:00 that
morning. We had gears lying around, but no shafts. Luckily, the box of pens we
had bought were a great fit! So I got busy making a replica of the chapel I had
hung eyes from the year before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/scav/map.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of many things we did not have time to make was a stand to hold it up.
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, ours was the only one with a building that had moving gears on
it. However, the motor that was supposed to lift the building up from under the
map burned out when we were presenting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During these three hours I learned how hard it was to work with foamcore
poster-board. But I forgot all about that when I started on Aquagraphics in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2013&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I assembled a Big Projects team! We could plan items together, build
them together, all that jazz. I spent a lot more time with the rest of the team,
helping people with their own technical items. This was much more fun than
working alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Liver&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;84. Take us on a Fantastic Voyage through your team’s larger-than-life
model of a human organ. Your structure must be able to comfortably
accommodate at least four tourists at a time and present an accurate
and informative account of the organ’s inner workings. We’ll happily
enter the body part of your choice, but remember that our heart belongs
to the Franklin Institute. [150 points]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/scav/liver-whole.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we are, shooing people into the liver.
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After much deliberation we settled on a liver. Because I like steel, we bought a
ton of electrical conduit and bent it into a frame. It was much lighter and
stiffer than a comparable wooden or PVC one. We covered it in about 80 feet of
chicken wire. When we started tarping the liver, we found that it was so light
that it blew away! So we got some rope and stakes to keep it on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/scav/liver-internal.jpg"  style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We filled the inside with clear plastic tubes to represent the tubes inside the
liver. We hooked up some "bodily fluids" to the tubes: a bottle of sweet tea
vodka for bile and red Gatorade for blood. We also had long twisty balloons so
visitors could "fold their own proteins."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="images/scav/liver-faces.jpg" 
style="width: 400px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the people who helped!
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Aquagraphics Curtain&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;208. An aquagraphic-style water curtain that displays your team name or
logo. [250 points]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://http://jdangerx.github.io/blog/208.html"&gt;See my other post.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="scav"></category></entry></feed>